<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<rfc category="std" submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-ietf-dnssd-update-lease-08" ipr="trust200902"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="3"
     scripts="Common,Latin" sortRefs="false" consensus="true"
     symRefs="true" tocDepth="3" tocInclude="true" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev='DNS Update Leases'>
      An EDNS(0) option to negotiate Leases on DNS Updates
    </title>

    <author initials='S' surname='Cheshire' fullname='Stuart Cheshire'>
      <organization>Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Apple Park Way</street>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>California</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 974 3207</phone>
        <email>cheshire@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="T" surname="Lemon" fullname="Ted Lemon">
      <organization>Apple Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 958</street>
          <city>Brattleboro</city>
          <region>Vermont</region>
          <country>United States of America</country>
          <code>05302</code>
        </postal>
        <email>mellon@fugue.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date>2023-07-07</date>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>DNS Update</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes an EDNS(0) option that can be used by DNS Update Requestors and
      DNS servers to include a lease lifetime in a DNS Update or DNS Update Response, allowing a server to garbage collect stale
      resource records that have been added by DNS Updates</t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>About This Document</name>
      <t>
        The latest revision of this draft can be found at <eref target="https://dnssd-wg.github.io/draft-ietf-dnssd-update-lease/draft-ietf-dnssd-update-lease.html"/>.
        Status information for this document may be found at <eref target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-dnssd-update-lease/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Discussion of this document takes place on the
        DNSSD Working Group mailing list (<eref target="mailto:dnssd@ietf.org"/>),
        which is archived at <eref target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/dnssd/"/>.
        Subscribe at <eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/dnssd/"/>.
      </t>
      <t>Source for this draft and an issue tracker can be found at
        <eref target="https://github.com/dnssd-wg/draft-ietf-dnssd-update-lease"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>Dynamic Updates in the Domain Name System <xref target="RFC2136"/> allows for a mapping from a persistent
      hostname to a dynamic IP address. This capability is particularly
      beneficial to mobile hosts, whose IP address may frequently change
      with location. However, the mobile nature of such hosts often means
      that dynamically updated Resource Records (RRs) are not properly
      deleted. Consider, for instance, a mobile user who publishes address
      RRs via DNS Update. If this user moves
      their laptop out of range of the Wi-Fi access point,
      the address RR containing stale information
      may remain on the server indefinitely.
      An extension to DNS Update is
      thus required to tell the server to automatically delete resource
      records if they are not refreshed after a period of time.</t>
    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Conventions and Terminology Used in this Document</name>
      <t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
	"MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
      <section>
	<name>Abbreviations</name>
	<dl>
	  <dt>DNS-SD</dt><dd>DNS-based service discovery <xref target="RFC6763"/></dd>
	  <dt>EDNS(0)</dt><dd>Extension Mechanisms for DNS, version 0 <xref target="RFC6891"/></dd>
          <dt>Update Lease option</dt><dd>Update Lease EDNS(0) option</dd>
          <dt>Lease Update Request</dt><dd>DNS Update Request containing an Update Lease option</dd>
          <dt>Lease Update Response</dt><dd>DNS Update Response containing an Update Lease option</dd>
          <dt>RR</dt><dd>Resource Record</dd>
	</dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Mechanisms</name>
      <t>The Update Lease EDNS(0) option is included in a standard DNS Update Request <xref
      target="RFC2136"/> within an EDNS(0) OPT pseudo-RR <xref target="RFC6891"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="update">
      <name>Lease Update Request Format</name>
      <t>
      Lease Update Requests and Responses are formatted as standard DNS 
      Update Requests <xref target="RFC2136"/>. Such Requests MUST include the EDNS(0) OPT RR, as
      described in <xref target="RFC6891"/>.  This OPT RR MUST include an EDNS(0) Option as shown
      below.</t>

      <t>The Update Lease EDNS(0) option is formatted as follows:</t>

<figure align="center" anchor="lease_opt" suppress-title="true"><artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
Field Name       Field Type   Description
----------------------------------------------------------------
OPTION-CODE      u_int16_t    UPDATE-LEASE (2)
OPTION-LENGTH    u_int16_t    4 or 8
LEASE            u_int32_t    desired lease interval (Lease Update Request) or
                              granted lease interval (Lease Update Response), in seconds
KEY-LEASE        u_int32_t    optional desired (or granted)
                              key lease interval for KEY RRs, in seconds
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>Lease Update Requests contain, in the LEASE field of the OPT RDATA, an
      unsigned 32-bit integer indicating the lease interval, or lease, in seconds, desired
      by the Requestor, represented in network (big-endian) byte order.
      In Lease Update Responses, this field contains the actual
      lease granted by the server. The lease granted by the
      server may be less than, greater than, or equal to the value
      requested by the Requestor.</t>

      <t>There are two variants of the Update Lease option,
      the basic (4-byte) variant and the extended (8-byte) variant.</t>

      <t>In the basic (4-byte) variant, the LEASE indicated in the
      Update Lease option applies to all RRs in the Update section.</t>

      <t>In the extended (8-byte) variant, the Update Lease communicates two lease lifetimes.
      The LEASE indicated in the Update Lease option applies to all RRs in the
      Update section *except* for KEY RRs.  The key lease interval indicated in the Update Lease
      option applies to KEY RRs in the Update section.</t>

      <t>The reason the KEY RR can be given a special lease time is that this RR is used
      in the DNS-SD Service Registration Protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-srp"/> to reserve
      a name (or names) when the service is not present.</t>

      <t>In the case of a KEY RR and some other RR, obviously the key lease interval applies to
      the KEY RR, and the LEASE applies to the other RR. If more than one RR that is not
      a KEY RR is added by the update, the lease interval (not the key lease interval) is applied to all such
      RRs. RRs that are removed are permanently removed.</t>

      <section anchor="update-refresh">
	<name>Types of Lease Update Requests</name>
	<t>This document describes two types of Lease Update Requests: Registrations and Refreshes. A
	Registration is a Lease Update Request that is intended to add information not already
	present on the DNS server. A Refresh is intended simply to renew the lease on a previous
	Registration without changing anything. Both requests are Lease Update Requests, so the
	term "Lease Update Request" is to specify behavior that is the same for both types of
	Lease Update Request.</t>

	<t>In some cases it may be necessary to add new information without removing old information.
	For the purpose of this document, such Requests are referred to as Registration Requests, although
	in effect they may also refresh whatever information is unchanged from a previous Registration Request.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Requestor">
	<name>Requestor Behavior</name>
	<t>DNS Update Requestors MUST send an Update Lease option with any Lease Update Request that is
	not intended to be present indefinitely. The Update Lease option SHOULD specify a lease
	interval that is no shorter than 1800 seconds (30 minutes). Requestors MAY specify a
	shorter lease if they anticipate that the RRs being updated will change sooner than
	30 minutes.  Requestors that expect the updated RRs to be relatively static SHOULD
	request appropriately longer lease intervals.</t>

	<t>If the DNS Response received by the Requestor does not include an Update Lease option,
	this is an indication that the DNS server does not support the Update Lease option. The
	Requestor SHOULD in this case continue sending Refresh Requests (see below) as if the
	server had returned an identical Update Lease option in its Response.</t>

	<t>If the DNS Response does include an Update Lease option, the Requestor MUST use the
	interval(s) returned in this option when determining when to send Refresh Requests. This
	is true both if the interval(s) returned by the server are shorter and if they are
	longer.</t>

	<t>When sending a Registration, the Requestor MUST delay the initial transmission by a
	random amount of time across the range of 0-3000 milliseconds, with a granularity of no
	more than 10 milliseconds. This prevents synchronization of multiple devices of the same
	type at a site upon recovery from a power failure. This requirement applies only to the
	initial Registration on startup: since Refreshes include a random factor as well, any
	synchronization that occurs after such an event should quickly randomize.</t>

	<t>Note: the requirement for 10ms granularity is a scheduling requirement intended to
	result in an even spread of Lease Update Requests, so that every such request doesn't come an exact number
	of seconds after startup. This requirement should not be construed as requiring anything
	of the link layer on which the packet is transmitted: the link layer may well impose its
	own constraints on the timing at which a Request is sent, and this document does not
	claim to override such constraints.</t>

	<t>Note: the reason for the 3000ms (three second) random interval as opposed to some
	other random interval is to allow for enough time to meaningfully spread the load when
	many devices renew at once, without delaying so long that the delay in discovery of
	devices becomes obvious to an end user. A 3-second random delay means that if there are
	for example 100 devices, and the random number generator spread is even, we would have
	one renewal every 30ms.  In practice, on relatively constrained devices acting as SRP
	servers, we are seeing the processing time for an SRP registration taking on the order
	of 7ms, so this seems reasonable.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Server Behavior</name>
	<t>DNS Servers implementing the Update Lease option MUST include an Update Lease option
	in response to any successful DNS Update (RCODE=0) that includes an Update Lease option.
	Servers MAY return different lease interval(s) than specified by the Requestor, granting
	relatively longer or shorter leases to reduce network traffic due to Refreshes, or
	reduce stale data, respectively.</t>
        <t>Note that both the 4-byte and 8-byte variant are valid on both clients and servers, but
	clients and servers may exist that do not support the newer 8-byte variant. Therefore,
	clients and servers that do support this variant must account for the possibility that
	the server with which they are communicating does not.</t>
	<t>A client that receives a 4-byte variant from a server when it sent an 8-byte variant
	MUST treat the 4-byte variant as specifying both the lease interval and the key lease interval.
	A server that supports the 8-byte variant MUST treat the 4-byte variant as specifying
	both the lease interval and the key lease interval. When a server receives a 4-byte variant, it
	MUST respond with a 4-byte variant. In this case the KEY and the other RRs expire at
	the same time.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="refresh">
      <name>Refresh Requests</name>

      <t>A Refresh Request is a DNS Update Request that is sent to the server after an initial
      DNS Update has been sent, in order to prevent the update's RRs from being garbage
      collected.</t>

      <section>
	<name>Refresh Request Format</name>

        <t>Refresh Requests are formatted like Lease Update Requests and Responses (see
        <xref target="update"/> "Lease Update Request Format"). The Refresh Request is
        constructed with the assumption that the result of the previous Registration or Refresh is
        still in effect. The Refresh Request will, in the case that the RRs added in a
        previous Lease Update Request were for some reason garbage collected, result in those RRs being
        added again.</t>

	<t>The Refresh Request SHOULD NOT include any Lease Update Request prerequisites that would fail if
	the Requestor's previous Registration or Refresh Request is still in effect. It also SHOULD NOT
	include prerequisites that would fail if the RRs affected by the previous Registration or
	Refresh Request are no longer present--that is, the Refresh Request should also work as a Registration Request.
	There may be cases where this is not possible, in which case the DNS Response from
	the server can be used to determine how to proceed when the Refresh Request fails.</t>

	<t>A Lease Update Request that changes the server state resulting from a previous Refresh or
	Registration is a Registration, not a Refresh.</t>

	<t>The Update Lease option in a Refresh Request contains the desired new lease interval for
	Requests, and the actual granted lease interval for Lease Update Responses. The lease interval indicated in the
	Update Lease option applies to all RRs in the Update section of the Refresh
	Request, except that if a key lease interval is included as well, that interval applies
	to any KEY RRs included in the Update section.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Requestor Behavior</name>

	<t>A Requestor that intends that its RRs from a previous update, whether a Registration
	or a Refresh, remain active, MUST send a Refresh Request before the lease interval elapses, or else the RRs
	will be removed by the server.</t>

	<t>In order to prevent RRs expiring, Requestors MUST refresh RRs before they
	expire. At the time of registration, the client computes an interval that is 80% of the lease
	interval plus a random offset between 0 and 5% of the lease interval. The random offset is to prevent
	refreshes from being synchronized. When this interval has expired, the client MUST send a Refresh
	if the data in the initial Registration should continue to be advertised.</t>

	<t>For Refresh Requests, the server is expected to return an Update Lease option, if
	supported, just as with the initial Registration. As with the Registration, the
	Requestor MUST use the interval(s) specified by the server when determining when to send
	the next Refresh Request.</t>

	<t>When sending Refresh Requests, the Requestor MUST include an Update Lease option, as
	it did for the initial Registration. The Update Lease option MAY either specify the same
	intervals as in the initial Registration, or MAY use the values returned by the server
	in the previous Lease Update Response, whether it was in response to a Registration a
	Refresh. As with Responses to Registrations, the Requestor MUST use the intervals
	returned by the server in the Response when determining when to send the next Refresh
	Request.</t>

	<section>
	  <name>Coalescing Refresh Request</name>
          <t>If the Requestor has performed multiple successful Registrations with a single server,
          the Requestor MAY send a Refresh Request containing all RRs from each previously-successful Registration Request to that server.
          This effectively places all RRs for a Requestor on the same expiration
          schedule, reducing network traffic due to Refreshes.</t>

	  <t>In doing so, the Requestor includes in the Refresh Request all existing RRs previously successfully registered on the server,
	  including those not yet close to expiration, so long as at least one
	  RR in the Request has elapsed at least 75% of its original lease interval. If the
	  Requestor uses UDP, the requestor MUST NOT coalesce Refresh Requests if doing so would
	  cause truncation of the Request; in this case, the Requestor should either send multiple
	  Requests or should use TCP to send the complete Request at once.</t>

	  <t>Requestors SHOULD NOT send a Refresh Request when all of the RRs in the
	  Refresh Request have more than 50% of their lease interval remaining before expiry. However,
	  there may be cases where the Requestor needs to send an early Refresh, and it MAY do
	  so. For example, a power-constrained (sleepy) device may need to send an Refresh Request when the radio
	  is powered so as to avoid having to power it up later.</t>

	  <t>Another case where this may be needed is if the lease interval registered with the
	  server is no longer appropriate and the Requestor wishes to negotiate a different
	  lease interval. However, in this case, if the server does not honor the requested
	  interval in its Response, the Requestor MUST NOT retry this negotiation.</t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section>
	<name>Server Behavior</name>
        <t>Upon receiving a valid Refresh Request, the server MUST send an acknowledgment. This
        acknowledgment is identical to the Lease Update Response format described in <xref
        target="update"/> "Lease Update Request Format", and contains the new lease interval of the resource
        records being Refreshed.  The server MUST NOT increment the serial number of a zone
        as the result of a Refresh.</t>

	<t>However, the server's state may not match what the client expects.  In this case, a
	Refresh may actually appear to be a Registration, from the server's perspective. If the
	Refresh changes the contents of the zone, the server MUST update the zone serial
	number.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Retransmission Strategy</name>
      <t>The DNS protocol, including DNS updates, can operate over UDP or TCP. When using UDP, reliable
      transmission must be guaranteed by retransmitting if a DNS UDP message is not acknowledged in a
      reasonable interval. <xref target="RFC1035" section="4.2.1" sectionFormat="of"/> provides some
      guidance on this topic, as does <xref target="RFC1536" section="1" sectionFormat="of"/>.
      <xref target="RFC8085" section="3.1.3" sectionFormat="of"/> also provides useful guidance that
      is particularly relevant to DNS.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Garbage Collection</name>

      <t>If the lease interval of a RR elapses without being refreshed, the server
      MUST NOT return the expired RR in answers to queries. The server MAY delete the RR
      from its database. The lease interval(s) returned by the server to the Requestor are used
      in determining when the lease on a RR has expired.</t>

      <t>For all RRs other than a KEY RR included in a DNS Update request, the
      lease interval is the LEASE value in the Update Lease option. For KEY RRs, if the
      optional KEY-LEASE value was included, this interval is used rather than the interval
      specified in LEASE. If KEY-LEASE was not specified, the interval specified in LEASE is
      used.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t><xref target="RFC2136" section="8" sectionFormat="of"/> describes problems that can occur
      around DNS updates.  Servers implementing this specification should follow these recommendations.</t>

      <t>Several additional issues can arise when relying on the Update Lease option. First, a
      too-long lease interval is not much different than no lease: the RRs associated with
      this lease interval will effectively never be cleaned up. Servers implementing Update Lease
      should have a default upper bound on the maximum acceptable value both for the LEASE and
      KEY-LEASE values sent by the client. Servers MAY provide a way for the operator to change
      this upper limit. Default values for these limits of 24 hours and 7 days, respectively,
      are RECOMMENDED.</t>

      <t>The second issue is that a too-short lease interval can result in increased server load as
      Requestors rapidly renew their leases. A delay in renewing could result in the data being
      removed prematurely.  Servers implementing Update Lease MUST have a default minimum lease
      interval that avoids this issue. We RECOMMEND a minimum of 30 seconds for both the lease
      and key lease intervals. However, in most cases, much longer lease intervals (for example, an hour)
      are RECOMMENDED.</t>

      <t>There may be some cost associated with renewing leases. A malicious (or buggy) client
      could renew at a high rate in order to overload the server more than it would be
      overloaded by query traffic. This risk is present for regular DNS updates as well. The
      server MUST enforce a minimum interval between updates. After a Refresh or Registration
      has been successfully processed and acknowledged, another Update of either type from the
      client during that interval MUST be silently ignored by the server.</t>

      <t>Some authentication strategy should be used when accepting DNS updates. Shared secret
      <xref target="RFC8945"/> or public key signing (e.g. SIG(0) <xref target="RFC2931"/>) should be required. Keys should have limited
      authority: compromise of a key should not result in compromise of the entire contents of one
      or more zones managed by the server. Key management strategy is out of scope for this document.
      An example of a key management strategy can be found in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-srp"/>,
      which uses "First Come, First-Served naming" rather than an explicit trust establishment process,
      to confer update permission to a set of RRs.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <t>The EDNS(0) OPTION CODE 2 has already been assigned for this DNS extension. This
      document appears in the DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT) registry <xref target="EDNS0Codes"/> with the name 'UL' and the status 'On-hold,' and a
      document reference to an older version of this document. When this document has been
      approved, the IANA is asked to update the registry as follows:</t>
      <sourcecode>
    OLD:
        Value: 2
        Name: UL
        Status: On-hold
        Reference: http://files.dns-sd.org/draft-sekar-dns-ul.txt

    NEW:
        Value: 2
        Name: Update Lease
        Status: Standard
        Reference: [this document]
      </sourcecode>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>Thanks to Marc Krochmal and Kiren Sekar for their work in 2006 on the precursor to this
      document.  Thanks also to Roger Pantos and Chris Sharp for their contributions. Thanks to
      Chris Box, Esko Dijk, Jonathan Hui, Peter van Dijk, Abtin Keshvarzian, Nathan Dyck, Steve
      Hanna, Gabriel Montenegro, Kangping Dong, and Tim Wicinski for their working group reviews of this document.
      Thanks to David Dong, Olafur Gudmundsson, Brian Trammel, and Shivan Sahib for their directorate
      reviews and IANA reviews.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
<!-- This needLines directive is to keep the Authors' Addresses heading from being split from the list -->
    <!-- <displayreference target="I-D.sctl-service-registration" to="RegProt"/> -->
    <!-- <displayreference target="I-D.ietf-dnssd-hybrid" to="I-D.ietf-dnssd-hybrid"/> appears to not work in xml2rfc 2.6.2 -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1536.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2931.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6763.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8085.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8945.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnssd-srp.xml"/>
      <reference anchor="EDNS0Codes" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters/dns-parameters.xml">
        <front>
          <title>DNS EDNS0 Option Codes (OPT)</title>
          <author/>
          <date month="April" year="2023"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
